U.S. Board of Inquiry on the 1959 Labor Dispute in the Steel Industry Records 5074
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Board of Inquiry on the 1959 Labor Dispute in the Steel Industry Records
1960
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Board of Inquiry
Steel Companies Coordinating Committee
5074
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Proceedings, reports (documents), transcripts.
Steel Companies Coordinating Committee vs. United Steelworkers of America: documents, 1959-1960. Consist of the transcripts of the proceedings (2 vol.), the Board's final report, and the exhibits submitted by the union and the steel companies.
3336732
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 07, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 28, 2016
Biographical / Historical
This Board of Inquiry was created on October 9, 1959 by President Dwight David Eisenhower according to powers granted him under the national emergencies section of the Taft-Hartley Act. The Board was empowered to investigate the dispute which led to an industry-wide steel strike by the United Steelworkers of America (USWA).
The dispute began on April 10, 1959, when the steel companies proposed that the collective agreement that was due to expire on June 30 be extended another year without alteration. Rejecting this suggestion, the union asked for a new agreement which was to include a twelve cents per hour increase, a cost-of-living adjustment, and improved fringe benefits. When no progress in negotiations occurred despite an extension of one month in the agreement, the USWA called a strike on July 15th. The October 19 report of the Board was without effect and, at the direction of the president, the attorney general began an injunction action against the strike which took effect on November 7th. The Board was reconvened on November 10th and issued its second report on January 6th, 1960. The major road blocks to settlement identified by the Board were the dispute over a wage increase and the differences over work rules, with the companies insisting that the total package could not exceed 2.7 percent. On January 15, an agreement was signed that provided for a seven cents per hour pay increase, a cost-of-living adjustment and improved pension and health benefits.
Scope and Contents
Consist of the transcripts of the proceedings (2 vol.), the Board's final report, and the exhibits submitted by the union and the steel companies.
Union exhibits before the first Board include a statement of issues and the position of the union by its attorney, Arthur J. Goldberg; correspondence between the union and the major steel corporations, April-October, 1959; a brief by Goldberg on the -national emergency issue; a brief by Leon H. Keyserling on the steel strike and the recession of 1958; a brief by Meyer Bernstein on the issue of foreign competition; and briefs by staff officers of the union on other specific economic issues.
Major steel companies involved in the strike include the Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation, ARMCO Steel Corporation, Bethlehem Steel Corporation, Great Lakes Steel Corporation, Inland Steel Company, Jones & Laughlin Steel Company, Raiser Steel Corporation, United States Steel Corporation, Wheeling
United States. Board of Inquiry on the 1S59 Labor(CONTINUED} Steel Corporation and Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company, among others. Exhibits presented by this group include a statement of management's position, correspondence between the corporations and the union, April-July, 1959, statistics bearing on the dispute, and statements on inflation, profits, and foreign competition, among other documents.
Exhibits submitted to the second hearing include exchangee of offers between the union and individual companies; statements on behalf of the union by Goldberg, David J. McDonald, USWA president, and George Meany; and statements on behalf of management by R. Conrad Cooper and K.C. Lumb, among other documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5073: U.S. Board of Inquiry to Report on Certain Labor Disputes Affecting the Maritime Industry of the United States Records
Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Iron and steel workers; Employee fringe benefits -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Health insurance -- United States; Health insurance -- Law and legislation -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Steel industry -- United States; Retirement -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Steel industry -- United States; Wages -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Steel industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Allegheny Ludlum Steel Corporation; ARMCO Steel Corporation; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; Colorado Fuel and Iron Company; Great Lakes Steel Corporation; Inland Steel Company; Jones & Laughlin Steel Company; Kaiser Steel Corporation; Republic Steel Corporation; United States. Board of Inquiry on the 1959 Labor Dispute in the Steel Industry; United States Steel Corporation; United Steelworkers of America; Wheeling Steel Corporation; Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company; Bernstein, Meyer; Cooper, R. Conrad; Goldberg, Arthur J.; Keyserling, Leon H. (Leon Hirsch), 1908-1987; Lehaczky, Paul M.; Lumb, H. C.; McDonald, David J. (David John), 1902-1979; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Perkins, John A.; Taylor, George William, 1901-
3336732
- Exhibits, Transcripts, Reports (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2 Presidential Board of Inquiry - United Steel Workers of America and Certain Companies in the Steel Industry (2nd Hearing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 12 Companies (Steel Companies Coordinating Committee) Exhibits A-J3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Exhibits, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    April 13, 1959.
  - 15 Companies (Other Steel Companies) Exhibit A (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Iron Ore Companies Exhibits A-B1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 11 Steel Companies (2nd Hearing) A-J (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Union Exhibits C-G (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Union Exhibits K-S6, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Union Exhibits K-S6, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Union Exhibits (2nd Hearing) A-R, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    July 14, 1959.
  - Union Exhibit H-J Appendix E, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    July 3, 1951.
  - Union Exhibits B-11 - B-18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 11. Arbitration Decision., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    July 13, 1957.
  - 12. Decision of Impartial Umpire., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    May 18, 1959.
  - 13. Arbitration of Decision., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    January 31, 1953.
  - 14. Recommendations of Wage Stabilization Board. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 15. Non-Economic Proposals - United States Steel., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    September 8, 1959.
  - 16. Report to United States Steel Local Unions., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    September 17, 1959.
  - 17. Report to Bethlehem Local Unions., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 18. Report to Bethlehem Negotiating Committee., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    September 25, 1959.
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit C. The National emergency Issue - Arthur J. Goldberg. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit D. An Economic Documentation of the Steelworkers Position in the 1959 Steel Strike - Otis Brubaker, Director, Research Department, United Steelworkers of America. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit E. Statement by Robert R. Nathan, Consulting Economist, United Steelworkers of America. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit F. The Steel Strike of 1959 and the Recession of 1958 - Leon H. Keyserling, Former Chairman, Council of Economic Advisors, Consulting Economist and Attorney., 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit G. The Issue of Foreign Competition - Meyer Bernstein, International Affairs Representative, United Steelworkers of America. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1. Steelworkers' Conference Proceedings, Vienna, Austria., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    March 19-21, 1959.
  - 2. Minutes of Steelworkers' Conference, Vienna, Austria., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 3. Comparison of United States Steel and Bethlehem Employment Conditions in the United States and Venezuela., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    April 9, 1959.
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit H. The Union's Analysis of Contract Proposals - David Feller, Associate General Counsel. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit I. Supplemental Statement of the Issues and the Position of the Union - Salaried, Office and Technical Workers - John J. Pasting, Director, Office and Technical Department, United Steelworkers of America. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit J. Statement of the Union with Respect to Insurance, Pensions and Supplemental Unemployment Benefits. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Appendix A: Non-Contributory Insurance Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Appendix B: Pension Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Appendix C: Supplemental Unemployment Benefit Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Appendix D: Steel Industry's Proposal on Insurance Pensions and SUB. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Appendix E: Comparison of Age Pensions Under Basic Steel Industry Pension Plan and Under 25 Selected Non-Contributory Pension Plans. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit K. Union Statement on Status of Negotiations with Lake Shipping Companies. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit L. Union Statement on Iron Ore Negotiations. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit M. 1959 Wage Policy statement of International Wage Policy Committee. (Box 1, Folder 39)
    April 30-May 1, 1959.
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit N. Proposals of United Steelworkers of America for the 1959 Negotiations. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit O. Union's Offer., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    October 15, 1959.
  - 1. Calculation of Additional Pension Costs (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 2. Calculation of Industry Insurance Plan - Murrary W. Latimer, Industrial Relations Consultant., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit P. Union Comments on steel Industry's Insurance Proposal., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    October 17, 1959.
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit Q. Union Comments on SUB Offer of the Steel Companies. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit R. Union Comments on Pensions Offer of the Steel Companies. (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 1st Hearing. Exhibit S. Miscellaneous Exhibits Submitted by the Union at the End of Hearings. (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hearings. 1. Union Memorandum on Union Proposal of October 15 and Company Proposal of October 17., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    1959? No year specified.
  - Hearings. 2. Union Statement on Cost of Supplemental Unemployment Benefits., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hearings. 3. Union Statement of Cost-of-Living Proposal. (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Hearings. 4. The Wage Increase Proposals. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hearings. 5. Union Proposal - the Second Year Wage Increase. (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Hearings. 6. Salary Contract "Replacement Value" Considerations. (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit A. Statement of R. Conrad Cooper. (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit B. Statement of the Companies' Position. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - 1. Letter from Twelve Major Steel Companies to President, United Steelworkers of America., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    April 10, 1959.
  - 2. Letter from Twelve Major Steel Companies to President, United Steelworkers of America., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    June 10, 1959.
  - 3. Letter to Employees of the United States Steel from W.F. Munford, President., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    August 7, 1959.
  - 4. Extension Agreement Between United Steelworkers of America and Twelve Major Steel Companies., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    June 27, 1959.
  - 5. Letter from Twelve Major Steel Companies to President, United Steelworkers of America., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    July 12, 1959.
  - 6. Letter from twelve Major Steel Companies to President, United Steelworkers of America, in reply to Union Proposal., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - 7. Background Statistics Bearing on the Steel Dispute. (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - 8. Background Statistics Bearing on the Steel Dispute - Supplementary Tables. (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - 9. Steel Industry Review of Background Statistics Bearing on the Steel Dispute. (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - 10. Statement by R. Conrad Cooper on Behalf of the Negotiating Team for the Twelve Steel Companies. (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - 11. Economic Matters of Fact - A Steel Data Book., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    October 1, 1959
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit C. Companies' Statement on Employment Cost Competition. (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit D. Companies' Statement on Inflation. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit E. Companies' Statement on Profits. (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit F. Summary of Companies Statement on Foreign Competition. (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit G. Clarification of Position of the 12 Companies with Respect to the Contract Changes Covered by Paragraph 2 of the Companies Proposal., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    October 1, 1959.
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit H. Statement on Behalf of Great Lakes Steel Corporation - Seniority Issue. (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit I. Statement by H. Conrad Cooper., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    October 18, 1959.
  - 12 Companies. Exhibit J. Twelve Companies' Offer., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - 1. Summary of Estimates of Employment Cost Increases - Industry and Union Proposals. (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - 2. Estimates of Increased Company Cost of Insurance and Pension Proposals. (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - 3. The Estimated Employment Cost Impact to the Steel Industry of a One Cent Per Hour Increase in Wage Rates. (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - 15 Companies. Exhibit A. Statement of the Companies' Position. (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Iron Ore Companies. Exhibit A. Statement Submitted by Certain Iron Ore Companies - W.F. Montague. (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - 1. List of Iron Ore Mining Companies Involved in United Steelworkers strike. (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Iron Ore Companies. Exhibit B. Memorandum Submitted to Board of Inquiry by Certain Iron Mining Companies Operating in the Lake Superior District - W.F. Montague., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - 1. Table 1 - Estimate of Iron Ore Situation., 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Report to the President., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    October 19, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit A. Statement of David J. McDonald., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    December 28, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit B. Statement of George Meany. (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit C. Statement of United Steelworkers of America - Arthur J. Goldberg. (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit D. Summary of Companies' and Union Proposals (Based on United Sates Steel Proposals). (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit E. Union Proposal - Production and Maintenance Employees. (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit F. Union Proposal - Continental Can Company, Incorporated. (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit G. Union Proposal - Aluminum Company of America. (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit H. Union Proposal (S.U.B.) - Reynolds Aluminum Company. (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit I. Union Letter to Each Company Requesting Company by Company Bargaining. (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit J. Letter to United States Steel Corporation, Attention R. Conrad Cooper (For Each of the Eleven Companies and for Each Chairman). (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit K. Letter to the President of the United States from David J. McDonald., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    December 3, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit L. Letter to All Companies Covered by Taft-Hartley Injunction from David J. McDonald., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    December 9, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit M. Motion and Memorandum in Support of Motion - District Court, Western District of Pennsylvania. (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit N. Memorandum Regarding 2B Example in the Steel Companies' Coordinating committee Advertisement., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit O. Can Package (Can Industry). (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit P. Alcoa Settlement. (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit Q. Union Cost Estimates. (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - 2nd Hearing. Union Exhibit R. Letter from Arthur J. Goldberg to Chairman, Presidential Board of Inquiry., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    December 31, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit A. Opening Statements - R. Conrad Cooper. (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit B. Company Proposal to Union., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 103)
    November 15, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit C. List of Eleven Companies' Last Offers. (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit D. Explanation of the Eleven Companies' S.U.B. Proposals. (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit E. Comparison of Companies' and Union Proposals Regarding S.U.B. (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit F. Statement by H.C. Lumb. (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit G. Statement by R. Conrad Cooper. (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit H. Summary of Companies' Estimates of Employment Cost Increases - Companies' and Union Offers - Cents Per Hours Worked. (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit I. Price Waterhouse Cost Report. (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - 2nd Hearing. Companies' Exhibit J. Letter from R. Conrad Cooper to Chairman, Presidential Board of Inquiry., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - 2nd Hearing. Miscellaneous Exhibit. Statement of Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service. (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - 2nd Hearing. Miscellaneous Exhibit. Detailed Analysis of the Industry Proposal of November 15 and the Kaiser Settlement. (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - 2nd Hearing. Miscellaneous Exhibit. Letter from Steel Companies to David J. McDonald., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 114)
    December 19, 1959.
  - 2nd Hearing. Miscellaneous Exhibit. Memorandum of Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - 2nd Hearing. Miscellaneous Exhibit. Decision of Dissent of the Supreme Court on the Injunction. (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Transcripts. 2 Volumes, 182 Pages. (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Final report to the President., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 118)
    January 6, 1960.